<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Puppet | Questy.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://questy.org/blog/categories/puppet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://questy.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-17T15:40:53-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://questy.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jerald Sheets]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PuppetConf 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2015/10/27/puppetconf-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-27T22:11:28-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2015/10/27/puppetconf-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>PuppetConf Portland</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/logo.jpg" alt="PuppetConf" /></p>

<p>Ahh, Portland! What a great place to have PuppetConf this year. The home of Puppet Labs and all its varied food, drink, and other unnamed consumables give Portland a vibe like no other.</p>

<p>From the hipster eateries to the burger dives around town, Portland offered something for everyone.</p>

<p>My week began by arriving a tad early for the Puppet Certifed Consultant training day. On the way in, I passed this little beauty right here:</p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/mountain.jpg" alt="Mountain" /></p>

<p>I had forgotten just how beautiful the Pacific Northwest can be.</p>

<p>In our meetings before the conference began in earnest, we talked about things announced and things as yet unannounced, and essentially just learned how to be better consultants and puppeteers. It was nice to be able to ask the questions that arise from time to time of the “big boys” (Gary Larizza, Zak Smith, etc.) and get first-hand accounts on how to do better.</p>

<p>There were quite a number of really cool talks on various upcoming tech, that I had quite a bit of opportunity to take notes and build upon knowledge I’d already gained.</p>

<p><strong>Keynotes!!</strong></p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/keynote_wide.jpg" alt="KeynoteWide" /></p>

<p>Next up was the PuppetConf Keynotes for the first day that usually contains Luke Kanies' annual Puppet conversation. Where they’ve been, what they’re doing, and the roadmap forward was fodder for Luke’s talk, and you can find the complete Keynote <a href="https://puppetlabs.com/presentations/puppetconf-2015-lukes-keynote-address">here</a>:</p>

<p>The big synopsis I can give is all about application automation. For you Puppeteers out there, just think of the relationships between the File|Package|Service component “types” and apply that to application components (db, web, container, Java App, etc.) and you get the gist. Very cool, very powerful, and very near. Be looking for Puppet Enterprise 2015.3 to drop in the very near future. I’ll certainly have soe blog things to say when that happens.</p>

<p>I appreciate, once again, my employer <a href="http://shadow-soft.com">Shadow Soft</a> sending me out to PuppetConf to be the best engineer I can be, and learn all the new tricks and tools at my disposal while on the road.</p>

<p>Look for me to pick up where I left off with basic tools, and a revamp of my early-on configuration tutorial for Puppet Community with the new tools and features in Puppet 4 soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Puppets.. Puppets Everywhere]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2015/04/30/puppets-dot-puppets-everywhere/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-30T12:52:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2015/04/30/puppets-dot-puppets-everywhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>3.8 is Here!!!</strong></p>

<p>That’s right, kids. PE 3.8 has dropped, and it is quite tasty. Some highlights:</p>

<p><strong>AWS Module Now a Supported Module</strong></p>

<p>As simple as that sounds, it’s huge. Being able to stand up multiple, tens, even hundreds and thousands of servers into AWS at once with Puppet is a great thing, but to have the module supported by Puppet Labs Support is even better.</p>

<p><em>Docker Containers??</em></p>

<p>Indeed. The Node manager now “gets” Docker containers and you can provision from bare metal as needed. Once the provisioning is done, it hands directly off to Puppet to execute the configuration portion of your run. Seet, sweet sauce right there.</p>

<p><em>Bare Metal</em></p>

<p>You’ve always been able to foray into the world of bare metal provisioning, but now it too is supported for you. You can stand up OSes, hypervisors, and then hand those off into the config run using Razor. Razor is now core to PE and also supported by the Puppet Labs Support Team.</p>

<p><em>Code Management</em></p>

<p>A long time coming, you can also manage code deployment to your Puppet Master using r10k, installed by default. Newly dubbed the “Puppet Code Manager”, r10k remains a command line tool, but I hear rumblings there may be some GUI juice on the horizon for this.</p>

<p><strong>Deprecations</strong></p>

<p>As with any release, some Puppet Enterprise features are going the way of the Dodo Bird. Some expected, some surprising, Puppet Enterprise’s landscape is certainly changing.</p>

<p><em>Cloud Provisioner</em></p>

<p>Long decried as a weak part of the PE infrastructure, the newly announced AWS Supported Module renders it redundant, and as such is removed from the shipping product’s default installation. Of course, if you have a large infrastructure that leverages the Cloud Provisioner, you can continue to use it by installing it into PE separately.</p>

<p><em>Live Management</em></p>

<p>Live management, a long-standing feature of the Enterprise Console, is now also deprecated. Of course, with the new code management features “baked-in” to Puppet Enterprise through r10k, Live Management is somewhat redundant. However, Puppet Labs notes that they will be releasing improved resource management functionality in future releases. If you need Live Management, then just as you can with the Cloud Provisioner, you can turn it on as well in the 3.8.0 product.</p>

<p><strong>Compatability</strong></p>

<p>Finally, some older versions of supported OSes are no longer so, and the list is as follows:</p>

<p>centos-5-i386<br>
centos-5-x86_64<br>
centos-6-i386<br>
debian-6-i386<br>
debian-6-x86_64<br>
debian-7-i386<br>
debian-7-x86_64<br>
oracle-5-i386<br>
oracle-5-x86_64<br>
oracle-6-i386<br>
redhat-5-i386<br>
redhat-5-x86_64<br>
redhat-6-i386<br>
scientific-5-i386<br>
scientific-6-i386<br>
sles-11-i386<br>
ubuntu-1004-i386<br>
ubuntu-1004-x86_64<br>
ubuntu-1204-i386<br>
ubuntu-1404-i386<br></p>

<p>I’m sure you may have some of these in your infrastructure, but they’re usually the result of a vendor application’s supported platforms. If so, you may wish to communicate back upstream to your various vendors, because when you upgrade PE, these go away for you.</p>

<p><strong>Try It Out</strong></p>

<p>As usual, I’ve already created a Vagrant instance to allow you to test and work with the new PE, testing out your existing code on the new platform. Check it out on my GitHub here.</p>

<p>Let me know if you find any issues, and happy Puppeting!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PuppetConf 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2014/09/23/puppetconf-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-23T14:19:37-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2014/09/23/puppetconf-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Glad to be at PuppetConf with #ShadowSoft exploring all the latest and greatest in PuppetLabs.</p>

<p><a href="http://questy.org/images/puppetconf.jpg"><img src="http://questy.org/images/puppetconf.jpg" alt="puppetconf.jpg" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Toolbox Grows...]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2014/06/11/toolbox-grows/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-11T12:57:18-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2014/06/11/toolbox-grows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So far we&rsquo;ve gotten our heads around some important things.  First and foremost, vim.  Our editor and companion for creating great code and ways to see our code in action and be able to determine at a glance whether our syntax is correct.  Also, we&rsquo;ve looked at revision control.  The single largest &ldquo;CYA&rdquo; ohmygodimgladivegotanoldercopytorestoreto sort of paradigm where you can roll yourself back to previously &ldquo;known good&rdquo; revisions to save that day&hellip;besides that, it&rsquo;s just darned good practice to keep your code externally saved, revision controlled, and accessible.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also talked about importance of workflow clarity and quality.  If you implement a poor workflow, you just have an automated <em>poor </em>workflow. Key word here is &ldquo;poor&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Next up on our browse through the &ldquo;toolbox&rdquo; is &ldquo;Vagrant&rdquo;.  What is this Vagrant, you ask?</p>

<p>Virtualization is paramount in today&rsquo;s world in a number of ways and for a number of reasons.  For extending your server farms to handle even more application expression, to expand your own desktop machines to test/try different operating systems, and even just rolling up an ad-hoc VM so you can try something without touching a &ldquo;real&rdquo; machine in your environment.</p>

<p>Some may disagree, but I&rsquo;ve found virtualization to be one of the most powerful tools added to the toolbox in years.  Not only can you prototype systems or applications, but you can prototype entire environments.  This is where Vagrant shines, and especially in the context of Puppet (master + clients), allows you to create a fully functioning Puppet environment upon which to develop, prototype, and test without ever jeopardizing even the least important system of your infrastructure.  I count that as a &ldquo;win&rdquo;.  Let&rsquo;s see what this tool can do.</p>

<p><em><strong>What <em>is</em> Vagrant?</strong></em></p>

<p>According to its website:</p>

<p>Vagrant provides easy to configure, reproducible, and portable work environments built on top of industry-standard technology and controlled by a single consistent workflow to help maximize the productivity and flexibility of you and your team.</p>

<p>To achieve its magic, Vagrant stands on the shoulders of giants. Machines are provisioned on top of VirtualBox, VMware, AWS, or any other provider. Then, industry-standard provisioning tools such as shell scripts, Chef, or Puppet, can be used to automatically install and configure software on the machine.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot there, but it&rsquo;s just a fancy way of saying exactly what I said before.  Vagrant is essentially a framework system that wraps your virtualization engine to manage <em>environments </em>of VMs.  Here is where Vagrant will hold the power for us.</p>

<p><em><strong>Virtualization</strong></em></p>

<p>If Vagrant is the framework, then Virtualization is the foundation.  Now, I&rsquo;ve chosen to use &ldquo;Virtualbox&rdquo; for my virtualization technology, but VMWare works every bit as well.  I am doing all my testing over Virtualbox, however, so YMMV.  Virtualbox is freely available from oracle, and you can download the appropriate version from Virtualbox at <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org.">https://www.virtualbox.org.</a>  I am running the latest version at 4.3.12 (as of this writing) and it serves the Vagrant system extremely well.</p>

<p><em><strong>Vagrant</strong></em></p>

<p>Next, you&rsquo;ll need to install Vagrant on your system.  You can find all the right packages at <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com.">http://www.vagrantup.com.</a>  I am currently running version 1.6.3 without errors.</p>

<p>[warning]I want to make a disclaimer here since I&rsquo;ve had an issue or two with Vagrant on a platform I don&rsquo;t use-Windows.  I am a Mac &amp; Linux user, and have had no issues using the Vagrant/Virtualbox combo on either of these.  However, literally every time I&rsquo;ve used Vagrant over Windows, it&rsquo;s just been a mess.  I&rsquo;ve known one person (ONE!) who has gotten Vagrant to work over Windows, and it required his getting into the product, editing code, etc.  As such, I wouldn&rsquo;t recommend it for those new to the platform.[/warning]</p>

<p>On the Mac platform, you get a .dmg file and can extract it run the installer.  Linux versions are available as RPM installs and Debian Packages.  Once you&rsquo;re installed, let&rsquo;s mess around a bit with Vagrant to see what we can do.</p>

<p><em><strong>Getting Started</strong></em></p>

<p>Vagrant is a unique tool in that it allows you to manage all these varied VMs, but adds a twist.  The big twist is that you don&rsquo;t have to have the <em>source </em>materials for the VMs you&rsquo;re installing.  In fact, the simplicity of turning up a new VM is astounding.  Take the following series of commands:</p>

<p>cd <your favorite directory><br>
mkdir precise32<br>
cd precise32<br>
vagrant init hashicorp/precise32<br>
vagrant up<br></p>

<p>If your Vagrant is installed correctly, a number of things start to happen.  First, Vagrant places a file in your cwd called &ldquo;Vagrantfile&rdquo;.  Your vagrant file (indie) looks like this:</p>

<pre><code># -*- mode: ruby -*-
# vi: set ft=ruby :

# All Vagrant configuration is done below. The "2" in Vagrant.configure
# configures the configuration version (we support older styles for
# backwards compatibility). Please don't change it unless you know what
# you're doing.
Vagrant.configure("2") do |config|
  # The most common configuration options are documented and commented below.
  # For a complete reference, please see the online documentation at
  # https://docs.vagrantup.com.

  # Every Vagrant development environment requires a box. You can search for
  # boxes at https://atlas.hashicorp.com/search.
  config.vm.box = "hashicorp/precise32"

  # Disable automatic box update checking. If you disable this, then
  # boxes will only be checked for updates when the user runs
  # `vagrant box outdated`. This is not recommended.
  # config.vm.box_check_update = false

  # Create a forwarded port mapping which allows access to a specific port
  # within the machine from a port on the host machine. In the example below,
  # accessing "localhost:8080" will access port 80 on the guest machine.
  # config.vm.network "forwarded_port", guest: 80, host: 8080

  # Create a private network, which allows host-only access to the machine
  # using a specific IP.
  # config.vm.network "private_network", ip: "192.168.33.10"

  # Create a public network, which generally matched to bridged network.
  # Bridged networks make the machine appear as another physical device on
  # your network.
  # config.vm.network "public_network"

  # Share an additional folder to the guest VM. The first argument is
  # the path on the host to the actual folder. The second argument is
  # the path on the guest to mount the folder. And the optional third
  # argument is a set of non-required options.
  # config.vm.synced_folder "../data", "/vagrant_data"

  # Provider-specific configuration so you can fine-tune various
  # backing providers for Vagrant. These expose provider-specific options.
  # Example for VirtualBox:
  #
  # config.vm.provider "virtualbox" do |vb|
  #   # Display the VirtualBox GUI when booting the machine
  #   vb.gui = true
  #
  #   # Customize the amount of memory on the VM:
  #   vb.memory = "1024"
  # end
  #
  # View the documentation for the provider you are using for more
  # information on available options.

  # Define a Vagrant Push strategy for pushing to Atlas. Other push strategies
  # such as FTP and Heroku are also available. See the documentation at
  # https://docs.vagrantup.com/v2/push/atlas.html for more information.
  # config.push.define "atlas" do |push|
  #   push.app = "YOUR_ATLAS_USERNAME/YOUR_APPLICATION_NAME"
  # end

  # Enable provisioning with a shell script. Additional provisioners such as
  # Puppet, Chef, Ansible, Salt, and Docker are also available. Please see the
  # documentation for more information about their specific syntax and use.
  # config.vm.provision "shell", inline: &lt;&lt;-SHELL
  #   apt-get update
  #   apt-get install -y apache2
  # SHELL
end
</code></pre>

<p>Note that this is a long file with a lot of explanatory documentation.  In actuality, the most important part of your Vagrantfile can be summed up here:</p>

<pre><code># -*- mode: ruby -*-
# vi: set ft=ruby :
Vagrant.configure("2") do |config|
  config.vm.box = "hashicorp/precise32"
end
</code></pre>

<p>These are the lines that are uncommented plus the top two declaratives that tell Vagrant what to do.  It&rsquo;s a very simple file that does some very powerful things.  First, it checks your home directory in the ~/.vagrant.d location to see if you already have the &ldquo;precise32&rdquo; Vagrant source &ldquo;box&rdquo;.  (more on boxes later).  Next, if you do have this, it will simply start up a VM in your virtualization of choice with a randomized name.  For instance, mine is called &ldquo;precise32_default_1402504453444_30545&rdquo;.  Vagrant takes away the selection of an .iso image, connecting it to the virtual CD/DVD Rom, starting an installer, etc.  It simply sends you a pre-rolled image, places it in your .vagrant.d directory, and provisions the VM to respond to Vagrant commands, and starts it up within Virtualbox.  Precise32 is simply a test scenario, as Vagrant&rsquo;s site has quite a number of varied and specially configured &ldquo;box&rdquo; files that you can use to prototype on at their &ldquo;ready-made&rdquo; box discovery site: <a href="https://vagrantcloud.com/discover/featured.">https://vagrantcloud.com/discover/featured.</a>  You can install boxes with too many variations and differentiations to enumerate here, and that&rsquo;s not really the point for our purposes&hellip; you may find these of great assistance in your own workplace, but let&rsquo;s continue.</p>

<p>When you run your &ldquo;vagrant init&rdquo; command listed above, it places a Vagrantfile, and when you do a &ldquo;vagrant up&rdquo;, it automatically retrieves your box file, provisions, and starts the VM.  Now, by simply running &ldquo;vagrant ssh default&rdquo;, you are now logged into this virtual machine!  You also have full sudo to become root and do any sort of damage you may wish to do.  If you logout (&ldquo;exit&rdquo; or CTRL-D), and type &ldquo;vagrant destroy&rdquo;, the VM goes away and you have nothing in Virtualbox.</p>

<p>Were we to just stop here, the power inherent in being able to just have these &ldquo;Vagrantfiles&rdquo; (sort of like a &ldquo;Makefile&rdquo; for boxes) to spin up and down test scenarios at will is incredible.  But, let&rsquo;s look at this in light of the Vagrantfile, what it can do and how you can customize it.  There is an entire descriptive language surrounding Vagrant PLUS Vagrant has a plugin infrastructure whereby developers can extend Vagrant&rsquo;s capabilities.  We will capitalize on these later.</p>

<p>So, imagine a scenario where you can create a directory, copy a text file into it, run a single command, and it automatically provisions a 4-node Puppet Enterprise infrastructure, fully installed with a master and three agents, MCollective fully installed, PuppetDB installed and in use&hellip;  literally a full installation just like you would use for your infrastructure&hellip;  Now we get powerful.  NOW we have the ability to do some cool things.</p>

<p>Next time, that&rsquo;s exactly what we&rsquo;re going to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Do's and Dont's" for Your Puppet Environment]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2014/05/20/dos-donts-puppet-environment/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-20T09:15:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2014/05/20/dos-donts-puppet-environment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>IT Automation, like the features and functions offered by Puppet, is riddled with a number of pitfalls. Nothing dangerous or site-threatening in the near term, however evolving a <em>bad </em>plan can lead you down a painful path to re-trek when you ultimately need to demolish what you&rsquo;ve done and re-tool, re-work, or even re-start from scratch.  Some simple suggestions can help smooth your integration, and also provide tools and methodologies that make changes in philosophy easy to test and implement as well as make the long road back from a disaster easy(-ier?) to navigate.</p>

<p>Here are some simple guidelines that can provide that foundation and framework:</p>

<p><strong>DO <em>Always</em> Use Revision Control</strong></p>

<p>It would seem this would be a foregone conclusion in this day and age, but you would be surprised just how many shops don&rsquo;t have revision control of any kind in place.  A series of manifests or configurations might be tarred up and sent to the backup system, but aside from dated backups, there&rsquo;s no real versioning&hellip;just monolithic archives to weed through in a time of disaster.</p>

<p>Revision control puts you one command away from restoring those configurations and manifests (and even your data vis-a-vis &ldquo;Hiera&rdquo;) to their original locations in the most recent state.</p>

<p><strong>DO Rethink Your Environments</strong></p>

<p>If you automate a bad workflow, you still have a bad workflow.  (albeit an automated one!)</p>

<p>Rethink how you do things and why.  Why do you promote code the way you do, and is there a better way to do it?  Why do you still have a manual portion to your procedure, and is it entirely necessary, or can this be remanded to Puppet to do for you as well.  What things are you doing well?  How can they improve?</p>

<p>Try to think through all your procedures.  There are more than you think, and they&rsquo;re often less optimized than they can be.  If you&rsquo;re going to implement Puppet automation, it&rsquo;s time to retool.</p>

<p><strong>DO Implement Slowly and Methodically</strong></p>

<p>Another pitfall a lot of shops wander into is they try to do too much all at once, and do none of it well.  Either they implement too quickly and migrate a huge environment it took years to build (sometimes as much as a decade!) through a single professional services engagement or at an unrealistic pace.  Automation is complex, but if you take the time to implement correctly, piece-by-piece and hand-in-hand with your rethinking of your environment referred to above, you can revolutionize the way you work and make the environment considerably more powerful, considerably easier to work with, and ultimately release yourself to work on much more interesting problems in your environment.  Take your time to build the environment you want.</p>

<p><strong>DO Engage the Community</strong></p>

<p>By using Puppet, you are the beneficiary of the greatest software development paradigm in history &ndash; the Open Source movement.  People all over the world have taken part in crafting the powerful tool you have before you.  If you are able to help in like manner, by all means contribute your code to the community. (With your data in Hiera, this is easier than ever!)  Join a Puppet Users Group.  Share your clever solutions to unique problems with the community via GitHub, the Puppet Forge, your website&hellip; give back.  The more you pour in, the more you get out, and something you solve may end up baked into the final product one day in the future.</p>

<p><strong>DON&rsquo;T Pit Teams Against Each Other</strong></p>

<p>DON&rsquo;T make this a DEV vs OPS paradigm.  This is a marriage of the best tools of both worlds.  Depending on how your culture breaks down, this could be an OPS-aware way of doing development, or a DEV-informed way of doing operations.  You need to remember one thing in all of it.  The marriage of these worlds is a <em>teamwork</em> effort.</p>

<p>I was averse to the term DEVOPS when it first started being used, as it was a tool of the development world I was engaged with to cede root level access to developers.  In a properly managed, secure environment, this is always a no-no.  Development personnel are not trained systems people and rarely are.  By the same token, never ask your systems people to delve into core development, or to troubleshoot your developers' code.  They are not tooled for that work.</p>

<p>This does not say that one is better than the other, nor does it say they do not share a certain amount of core skills at the basest levels. Much like the differences between civil and mechanical engineers, each has a base level of knowledge that ties them together, but each is highly specialized.  You don&rsquo;t want your civil engineer building machine tools just as much as you don&rsquo;t want your mechanical engineer building bridges.  Each discipline is highly specialized and carries with it nuance and knowledge you only gain through experience&hellip;experience <em>on </em>the job.</p>

<p>Instead, find a culture and a paradigm that joins the forces of these two disciplines to build something unique and special rather than wasting time with dissension and argument.</p>

<p><strong>DON&rsquo;T Expect Automation to Solve <em>Everything</em></strong></p>

<p>I know, that sounds like a sacrilege at this point, but its true.  No matter how automated your site becomes, how detailed your configuration elements are, or how much you&rsquo;ve detailed your entire workflow, you still can never replace the element of human consideration and decision-making.</p>

<p>Automation, as I&rsquo;ve said before, automates away the mundane to make time for you, DEVOPS person, to work on really interesting and curious work.  You can now write that entire new whiz bang gadget you&rsquo;ve been conceptualizing for the last several years, but have never quite gotten there because you were too busy &ldquo;putting out fires&rdquo;.  Puppet automation is definitely a watershed in modern administration and development, but people are still needed.</p>

<p>Another &ldquo;intangible&rdquo; you may not readily think about when considering a DEVOPS infrastructure is one of <em>culture.  </em>The best places to work are always the best cultures brought about by the right collection of people, ideas, personalities, and management styles.  When you find that right mix of people and ideas, the workplace becomes a, forgive me, <em>magical</em> place to be.  Automation can never make that happen.</p>

<p><strong>DON&rsquo;T Starve Your Automation Environment</strong></p>

<p>Automation solves a lot of things, but one thing it cannot do is feed itself.  This particular animal has a ton of needs over time.  From appropriate hardware to personnel, the environment needs time, attention, and consideration.  Remember that this is the &ldquo;machine tool&rdquo; of your whole company.  It is the thing that builds and maintains other things.  As such, its priority rises above that of the next web server or DNS system.</p>

<p>Always allocate enough resources (read: money, personnel, and time) to your environment.  If that means engineer time to work on a specially project and to do the job <em>right</em>, that&rsquo;s what it means.  And, yes, it&rsquo;s more important than meeting an arbitrarily assigned &ldquo;live date&rdquo; to your new widget or site or application.  The environment comes first, and all else follows.  If you give the resources and time to your automation initiatives it deserves, a number of years down the road you will look back and be amazed at the sheer amount of work your team was able to accomplish just by keeping this simple precept.</p>

<p><strong>DON&rsquo;T Stop Evolving</strong></p>

<p>Never stop learning.  Never stop bettering yourself or your environment.  Always keep refactoring your code.  (i.e., if you wrote that Apache module 4 years ago, chances are good that what you&rsquo;ve learned in the interim can go back into making that module even better.)  Always keep your people trained and engaged on the latest developments in Puppet and all the associated tools.  Never stop striving to be better and never stop reaching.  I may sound lil your coach from high school in this, but those principles he was trying to impart hold true.  If you continue to drive forward and reinvent yourself as a regular part of your forward pursuits, the endpoint of that evolution will benefit you personally, your team both vocationally and culturally, your company&rsquo;s efficiency, and your environment&rsquo;s impact on your bottom line.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>

<p>If we keep a stronger eye on our environment and tools that rises above the simple concept of &ldquo;that software I bought&rdquo; and &ldquo;fit it in between all the other things you have to do&rdquo; and give Puppet its proper place in our company, it can truly revolutionize your workflow.  However, when properly placed culturally and from a design, implementation, and workflow perspective, it can transform any shop on levels not readily observable when looking at the price tag or the resource requirements list.  DO let Puppet transform your environment and workflow and DON&rsquo;T be afraid to take the plunge.  It&rsquo;s exciting, challenging, and can easily take your company to the &ldquo;next level&rdquo;.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
