<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Puppet, | Questy.org]]></title>
  <link href="http://questy.org/blog/categories/puppet/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://questy.org/"/>
  <updated>2017-04-21T13:35:05-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://questy.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jerald Sheets]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scaling Puppet Enterprise - Part III - Additional Compilers]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2017/04/21/scaling-puppet-enterprise-part-iii-additional-compilers/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-21T09:32:47-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2017/04/21/scaling-puppet-enterprise-part-iii-additional-compilers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong><em>You should have completed a split install before beginning this section. You can find the Split Installation documentation at Puppet&rsquo;s Website, or the first installment of this tutorial <a href="http://questy.org/blog/2017/04/18/scaling-puppet-enterprise-part-ii-installation/">here</a>.  If you try and begin here, you might find yourself lost.</em></strong></p>

<h3>First, Some Philosophy</h3>

<p>The Puppet Enterprise documentation circa PE 2015.3.2 had some &ldquo;issues&rdquo;. Let me actually preface that, though. Puppet Labs' documentation is by far some of the most voluminous and in many respects most complete vendor documentation out there. I don&rsquo;t mean to disparage their work AT ALL. When it comes to the fact they even have documentation at this level, they&rsquo;re the &ldquo;bees knees&rdquo;.</p>

<p>However, I&rsquo;ve always written documentation to fit the &ldquo;grandma rule&rdquo;. My grandmother was a little 4 foot nothing Cajun woman with English as her second language.  She never used the first computer, still had a rotary phone when she passed away, and remained suspicious of anything technical.  She <em>was</em>, however, a voracious reader, keenly intelligent, and understood considerably more than you&rsquo;d expect on first glance. She also was a stickler for puncutation, grammar, and the like. In short, if my grandma couldn&rsquo;t read the documentation and follow a step-by-step process to install Puppet successfully, then its just either too complex, poorly formatted or unclear and needs to be simplified.</p>

<p>This causes a problem, of course. There are technologists out there that would become annoyed at repetition, verbosity around &ldquo;understood&rdquo; things, and spelling out each and every step along the way&hellip; even painfully. However, I feel it is the only <em>proper</em> way to document something. My rules are simple.</p>

<pre><code>1. Leave nothing to question
2. Be as verbose and clear as possible
3. Make sure everything is in order, step-by-step
</code></pre>

<p>By following this simple guideline, I feel I&rsquo;m doing more of a service to the reader than if I presumed on their level of sophistication with Puppet, Linux/UNIX, Windows, research capability, Google-foo or whatever.</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s dive in, shall we?</p>

<h2>HAProxy</h2>

<p>Seemingly counterintuitive, I want to next install the HAProxy we will use as a Load Balancer on the additional compilers.  By installing this first, we can utilize Puppet to install the HAProxy, and manage them automatically rather than doing a lot of ad-hoc work.</p>

<p>Also, by doing the proxy first,  the prerequisites are satisfied in their proper order, the Load Balancer exists before configuring additional compilers (to be able to utilize the dns_alt_names for the load balancer along with the compilers) and to have the GitLab in place and hosting the control_repo before turning on and configuring Code Manager.</p>

<h3>Hardware</h3>

<p>In the initial hardware list, I included a node called &ldquo;Compile Master&rdquo;.  This node  looked like:</p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/compile_master_specs.png" alt="Compile Master Specs" /></p>

<p>This node may seem like overkill, but disk and memory are cheap.  If you are scaling at this level, its better to not have to reinstall your Load balancer later. Keep in mind, you don&rsquo;t have to use HAProxy and can use a corporate Load Balancer here, but its configuration is outside the scope of this tutorial.</p>

<p>Once you&rsquo;ve provisioned the load balancer, ssh to the node as the root user, and use the &ldquo;frictionless installer&rdquo; to add your Puppet agent.</p>

<pre><code>curl -k https://master.example.com:8140/packages/current/install.bash | bash
</code></pre>

<p>When the client is fully installed, retrieve the Enterprise Console from your browser, and navigate to Nodes | Classification | Unsigned Certificates and select &ldquo;Accept All&rdquo;.  Finally, ssh to the instance as the root user and run <strong><em>puppet agent -t</em></strong> to finish the setup.</p>

<h2>Configure the Load Balancer</h2>

<p>At this point, the node is provisioned and you have a Puppet agent running on it, but you have as of yet not configured the HAProxy Load Balancer for use in the environment. The load balancer will be necessary to have in place prior to adding compile masters to your existing split installation. The following instructions guide you through setting up the HAProxy load balancer.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>SSH to the Puppet Master as root.  <em>(<strong>master.example.com</strong> in our list)</em></p></li>
<li><p>Install the HAPRoxy Forge Module on the master
<code>
puppet module install puppetlabs-haproxy
</code>
<br>
 <em>leave your root console open while performing steps 3-6</em></p></li>
<li><p>Retrieve the Enterprise Console in your browser</p></li>
<li><p>Select <strong>Nodes</strong> | <strong>Classification</strong></p></li>
<li><p>Create a New Classification Group called &ldquo;<strong>Load Balancer</strong>&rdquo;</p></li>
<li><p>Select the new group from the list and pin the node &ldquo;<strong>compiler.example.com</strong>&rdquo; into the new group.</p></li>
<li><p>In your open SSH session to <strong>master.example.com</strong>, create the profiles module to hold the configuration for HAProxy</p></li>
</ol>


<pre><code>cd /etc/puppetlabs/code/environments/production/modules

mkdir -p profiles/manifests

cd profiles/manifests
</code></pre>

<ol>
<li><p>Once you have changed to the profiles/manifests directory, create the loadbalancer.pp manifest.</p></li>
<li><p>Follow the documentation <a href="https://forge.puppet.com/puppetlabs/haproxy/readme">here</a> to configure HAProxy. When complete, the loadbalancer.pp manifest should resemble the following with IPs corrected for your particular instance:</p></li>
</ol>


<pre><code># Load Balancer Profile
class profiles::loadbalancer {

  class { 'haproxy': }

  # Main Proxy Listener
  haproxy::listen { 'compiler.example.com':
    collect_exported =&gt; false,
    ipaddress        =&gt; $::ipaddress,
    ports            =&gt; '8140',
  }

  # First Load balanced Compile Master
  haproxy::balancermember { 'compiler1.example.com':
    listening_service =&gt; 'compiler.example.com',
    server_names      =&gt; 'compiler1.example.com',
    ipaddress         =&gt; '10.0.1.24',
    ports             =&gt; '8140',
    options           =&gt; 'check',
  }

  # Second Load Balanced Compile Master
  haproxy::balancermember { 'compiler2.example.com':
    listening_service =&gt; 'compiler.example.com',
    server_names      =&gt; 'compiler2.example.com',
    ipaddress         =&gt; '10.0.1.25',
    ports             =&gt; '8140',
    options           =&gt; 'check',
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Once you have created this profile, retrieve the Puppet Enterprise Console in your browser and navigate to <strong>Nodes | Classification | Load Balancer</strong>.</p>

<ol>
<li>Selet the <strong>Classes</strong> tab.</li>
<li>Click the &ldquo;refresh&rdquo; button so the console will pick up your new loadbalancer.pp profile to classify your node with.</li>
<li>Under the &ldquo;Add new Class&rdquo; heading, select <strong>profiles::loadbalancer</strong> from the list that drops down.</li>
<li>Click &ldquo;Add Class&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Commit 1 Change&rdquo; at the bottom right of the page.</li>
<li>SSH back into <strong>compiler.example.com</strong> and run <strong>puppet agent -t</strong> to configure the Load Balancer.</li>
</ol>


<p>Your Load Balancer is now prepared to balance traffic to two catalog compilers (<em><strong>catalog1.example.com</strong> and <strong>catalog2.example.com</strong></em>) as listed in the above configuration.</p>

<h3>Notes</h3>

<hr />

<p>I noted when putting together the loadbalancer.pp profile above that I had previously used some REALLY ODD ip addresses in the balancer config.  Why? For the life of me I cannot recall. The original file looked like so:</p>

<pre><code># Load Balancer Profile
class profiles::loadbalancer {

  class { 'haproxy': }

  # Main Proxy Listener
  haproxy::listen { 'compiler.example.com':
    collect_exported =&gt; false,
    ipaddress        =&gt; $::ipaddress,
    ports            =&gt; '8140',
  }

  # First Load balanced Compile Master
  haproxy::balancermember { 'compiler1.example.com':
    listening_service =&gt; 'compiler.example.com',
    server_names      =&gt; 'compiler1.example.com',
    ipaddress         =&gt; '10.0.1.24',
    ports             =&gt; '8140',
    options           =&gt; 'check',
  }

  # Second Load Balanced Compile Master
  haproxy::balancermember { 'compiler2.example.com':
    listening_service =&gt; 'compiler.example.com',
    server_names      =&gt; 'compiler2.example.com',
    ipaddress         =&gt; '10.0.1.25',
    ports             =&gt; '8140',
    options           =&gt; 'check',
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>In my original implementation I set the ipaddres fields with some odd IP addresses. For info around how to fill those but ,the documentation gives some hints:</p>

<blockquote><p>ipaddresses: Optional. Specifies the IP address used to contact the balancermember service. Valid options: a string or an array. If you pass an array, it must contain the same number of elements as the array you pass to the server_names parameter. For each pair of entries in the ipaddresses and server_names arrays, Puppet creates server entries in haproxy.cfg targeting each port specified in the ports parameter. Default: the value of the $::ipaddress fact.</p></blockquote>

<p>Since I was originally setting these up in Digital Ocean, I used the IP space 159.203.x.x which belongs to Digital Ocean. I am guessing these were the hard IPs on the instances I stood up. Since the documentation above states these are optional, you have two options here.  Either leave those lines out of your config altogether, or manually set them to the IP Address of the instance you&rsquo;re using. Try each and do which works for you.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Your HAProxy Load balancer is now complete and ready to take traffic to the additional catalog compiler nodes. In installment IV, we&rsquo;ll begin to add in more components along the way to a fully developed LEI of Puppet Enterprise.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scaling Puppet Enterprise]]></title>
    <link href="http://questy.org/blog/2017/04/17/scaling-puppet-enterprise/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-17T16:06:11-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://questy.org/blog/2017/04/17/scaling-puppet-enterprise</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In my former life as a consultant, I had to install all manner of configurations of Puppet for clients.  Some were small and some were large, but none were <strong><em>VERY</em></strong> large.  One of the big things I was finding back then was there just wasn&rsquo;t a lot of publicly available information regarding doing a full install and scaling it large.</p>

<p>So, I took some &ldquo;research time&rdquo; on my own and started to build out the configurations according to Puppet Labs' (at the time&hellip; now just &ldquo;Puppet&rdquo;) documentation. The problem I was having was that the docs wouldn&rsquo;t ever lead me to a successful install following a chronolgical set of steps. I had to click into subpages, jump over to sub-sub configurations, and then jump back to the main docs to follow yet another trail down until I reached the end&hellip;lather, rinse, repeat.</p>

<p><strong>Some Caveats..</strong></p>

<p><strong>First</strong>, this is probably no longer a good &ldquo;HOWTO&rdquo; unless you&rsquo;re installing an older Puppet Enterprise. It was created between 2015.2 and 2016.x, and likely has some amount of artifacting related to those versions.</p>

<p><strong>Second</strong>, I&rsquo;m going by docs I&rsquo;ve recorded for my own use.  I wrote these as mentioned above through prototyping, tearing it down, starting again, and literally doing the entire install over and over until it worked &ldquo;as advertised&rdquo;. A lot of this was really just ordering things the right way, and finding documentaiton for various pieces online at Puppet&rsquo;s documentation site as well as blogs, conversations, and plain old trial and error. I certainly can&rsquo;t warrant anything to anybody for any reason. As with most open source/creative commons assets, &ldquo;it works for me, hope it works for you, and if it doesn&rsquo;t, sorry about that.&rdquo;</p>

<p><strong>Finally</strong>, I hope to use this as the springboard to start brain-dumping all my old notes, conversations, ideas, and other prototyping I did in my home lab.  There&rsquo;s still a fair amount of documentation I cannot use or touch because they belong to my former employer or Puppet Labs, so some things may be less than clear and usually because I&rsquo;m dancing around an NDA, noncompete, or just plain being a nice guy. If I inadvertently reveal something I shouldn&rsquo;t, chances are it could disappear without a trace, but I&rsquo;ll still make a note that I removed something, and try and replace whatever it is with published docs.</p>

<p>In short: I want to help the community, but I&rsquo;m walking a tightrope here, so please be kind.</p>

<p><strong>Format</strong></p>

<p>I hope to start easy with a decision making process for installing Puppet, how to choose a method, think about scale, and will likely have quite an opinionated view at times.  Once PE is installed, we&rsquo;ll add compilers, scale postgres, etc. but for starters, I hope to just have the following:</p>

<p>PE Master (MoM)<br>
Puppet DB<br>
PE Console<br>
HA Proxy Node for Compilers<br>
Two Catalog Compilers<br>
One ActiveMQ Hub<br>
Two ActiveMQ Spokes<br>
Two Agent Nodes for testing<br></p>

<p>I know that&rsquo;s quite a number of nodes to get started with, but this after all a large environment infrastructure, and we want to scale big.</p>

<p><strong>Required Nodes</strong></p>

<p>To put together all the required components for a good large installation, I&rsquo;ve settled on the below specs. You can change those as you see fit, but note that some of the disk space requirements and related were due to Puppet&rsquo;s documented requirements <em>at the time</em>.  YMMV, of course, but this is what I consider to be a base level installation if you intend on scaling into the multiple tens of thousands of nodes. Be sure that if you&rsquo;re going to size this down that you&rsquo;re still meeting Puppet&rsquo;s needs in regards to memory, cores, and disk.  <em>(for a current listing of Puppet&rsquo;s reuqirements, you can look <a href="https://docs.puppet.com/pe/latest/sys_req_hw.html">here</a> for more information.)</em></p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/prerequisites.png" alt="Puppet_Prerequisites" /></p>

<p>In addition, you&rsquo;ll need to be aware of firewall requirements for such an installation.  Puppet has documentation regarding firewall configurations and needed ports at their website <a href="https://docs.puppet.com/pe/latest/sys_req_sysconfig.html#for-large-environment-installations">here</a>, but I&rsquo;ll insert the image and recount the requirements here.</p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/lei_port_diagram.png" alt="Firewall_Ports" /></p>

<p>In short:</p>

<p><img src="http://cvquesty.github.io/images/firewall_ports.png" alt="Firewall_Ports" /></p>

<p>This is a close approximation to what you need to know.  Detailed charts found in the above links, and a &ldquo;point-by-point&rdquo; port and use list is available to review.</p>

<p>In short, I&rsquo;ve found it easiest to have all PE components on the same VLAN with no restrictions between them. If you are going to have a local firewall turned up on each node, you&rsquo;ll need to manage all the above communications as you see fit, but for the serving infrastructure (if in a secure environment, of course) you can likely drop host firewalls in favor of corporate ones.  In short, make it as easy on yourself as you see fit while balancing that toward your corporate security policy.</p>

<p>Finally, make sure DNS and NTP are all ready to go.  I can&rsquo;t tell you the number of times I&rsquo;ve had major issues trying to get all this working, and NTP was off, or DNS didn&rsquo;t propagate as expected (it&rsquo;s always DNS, right?) or some other similar seemingly unrelated piece was not restarted or some such. Just make sure that all nodes resolve to their respective FQDN from all nodes. Obviously, the easiest way to do this is to simply put them all in DNS. You <strong><em>can</em></strong> manage the host files manually, but why would you want to do that?</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re at this point and all ready to go, look to the next entry to get started.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
